Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim.
Today is episode 12 and we are going to do something called "visiting an art museum".
We've been talking about
how central it is to your practice.
All year we talk about how central it is
to see emptiness directly.
Now suddenly we've gone off in a little bit of a different way and we said the crucial thing is that you have to have the direct experience of bodhichitta.
And have this experience
where you meet every living being.
And I almost hesitate to talk about it too much because I don't want it to start to become a thing in a book or something like that.
It's an experience that you can have,
and that you should have,
and you can have it in this lifetime.
And again, I just repeat to imagine what it would be like if you met billions of beings in 20 minutes or something.
And you established this bond with each one where you know I will take care of you as if you're my own mother or you're my own father.
Try to imagine what your life would be like
if you could get to this experience.
And that's where we are now.
That's really where we are.
And then after this
we're going to go into the six perfections.
After we learn to think like a bodhisattva,
after we have that motivation.
You can have that motivation before,
but that's called sugarcane.
Sugarcane means-- it's a little bit hollow.
It's like bamboo.
You can have a serious commitment to help everybody in the world that you know of.
But it's a much different thing to have direct personal contact with each being and to make a commitment to them personally, each one.
So, at least keep that seed in your mind.
Keep that idea in your mind.
That somebody said,
that Geshe Michael said this is possible.
You can do it. You can reach that.
And that's crucial.
In this lam rim it's almost presented as the main act.
As the Rolling Stones playing.
Then there's a kind of a lousy band that plays before.
If you enjoy concerts, it's sometimes very frustrating to sit through the opening act because you're waiting for the band you really like.
The one that you bought the ticket for!
And then they come up for just a short time
and then they go off and some other
not so good band closes for them.
So, just remember we've been going from the steps of the path for a beginning person and a medium person,
and then we're gonna get to the main event
which is trying to have that experience.
Then we're going to do everything else,
like the six perfections. The six perfections
come after the main event.
And becoming a Buddha comes after the main event.
So it's very interesting.
Somewhere in there at the end is tantra,
is the diamond way.
Trying to use a way that you become a Buddha
within one lifetime.
Within this lifetime you become a Buddha. Guaranteed to become a Buddha during this one lifetime.
But Pabongka Rinpoche says,
even for that the main act has to be this experience.
This experience of a commitment to help every living being, a direct commitment, with every living being, that
"I will help you. I'll help you get there".
So then he talks about how necessary
this attitude is for the practice of the secret teachings to become a Buddha in one lifetime.
And he's still on that theme and
we're going to be on that theme during this episode.
This episode is called "Visiting an Art Museum".
I got Seiji and Tim here,
with their masks on mostly,
They are thinking, Geshe-la, what´s the art museum? What´s that all about?
Well, here we go.
So we're going to start with a quotation from a text by Arya Nagarjuna. THE Arya, right? That's his nickname.
@PHAGS PA.
The Arya.
@RIN CHEN PHRENG BA LAS,
,BDAG NYID DANG NI 'JIG RTEN 'DIS,
,BLA MED BYANG CHUB THOB 'DOD NA,
,DE YI RTZA BA BYANG CHUB SEMS,
,RI DBANG RGYAL PO LTAR BRTAN DANG,
This is a famous piece of poetry from Nagarjuna's advice to an indian King, @Udayibhadra.
He's giving him suggestions
about how to run his kingdom.
We're thinking to make a new management book with all of Nagarjuna's suggestions for kings.
I think that'd be interesting.
Some publisher in Japan wants that.
So maybe in my free time...
@,BDAG NYID DANG NI 'JIG RTEN 'DIS,
,BLA MED BYANG CHUB THOB 'DOD NA,
If you want to reach this place
where you can emanate billions of bodies
at the same time to help different people--
so whether you want to reach it,
or you want the whole world to reach it
this matchless state
@BLA MED
@DE YI RTZA BA
the root, the thing you have to get first
is @BYANG CHUB SEMS
You have to get this wish for Buddhahood.
Which now we know means making a direct connection with countless beings and making this commitment to each one of them.
In a finite amount of time,
which is also kind of amazing.
@RI DBANG RGYAL PO
means the king of the lords of mountains.
It means Mount Sumeru.
It's like the highest Himalayan mountain,
like Mount Everest.
Immovable.
In Indian philosophy, it's called
@druva
which means the axis of the entire world, and the whole world is built around this immoveable axis.
So he says @LTAR BRTAN DANG
You should make that wish to help everybody else as firm in your heart as the Himalayan mountains.
You can't move the Himalayan mountains.
The earth moves, those mountains don't move.
So your hope, your wish to help other people,
should be that stable.
It should be the core of your life.
It should be the immovable core of your life.
This attitude to want to help everybody.
What we've been saying is interesting: if you had that attitude towards countless beings,
then you would be sort of like the middle of the sun.
Your mental state would be twenty five million degrees.
And then things like the virus, coronavirus,
could not exist in your world. They would be burned up. They couldn't coexist with that motivation.
And I do think it's a cool idea that together
we could wipe out the coronavirus.
People say, oh that's naive.
But maybe the other approaches are naive.
@ SEMS 'DI MED NA NI,
If you don't have this attitude
@GSANG SNGAGS KYI BSKYED RIM BSGOM PA LHA KHANG LA LTAD MO BLTA BA LTA BU
There are two stages to the secret teachings.
The one lifetime Buddha teachings.
There are two stages.
They are @BSKYED RIM  and @RDZOGS RIM.
Yeay, I'm glad I didn't offer you guys money.
@BSKYED RIM means I don't know, raising the Buddha. Creating the Buddha.
And @RDZOGS RIM means finishing the Buddha.
And what it means is,
@BSKYED RIM  and @RDZOGS RIM,
@BSKYED RIM
means to make contact with divine beings.
To practice, meditate, do your yoga,
be nice to other people and then one day
you make contact with divine beings
That's the first stage of the secret teachings.
The second stage of the secret teachings is after you meet them, they start instructing you and helping you.
They have a unique insight into what you need, because they can read your mind and they can see your future.
So they're pretty good at suggesting
a course of action for you.
So that's called @RDZOGS RIM. When you study with them and you change into a Buddha.
That's called completion stage.
So he's talking here,
@GSANG SNGAGS KYI BSKYED RIM BSGOM PA,
if you don't have this attitude of bodhichitta,
if you haven't had that experience,
then meeting those divine beings will be like walking into a museum and looking at a painting.
So you can either--
I went to Paris and saw the Mona Lisa
with Veronica and her sister.
Actually we couldn't get too close to it,
because there were so many people.
Imagine the difference between looking at a painting of Mona Lisa and meeting Mona Lisa.
I think I would rather meet Mona Lisa.
I'd ask her why she has that smile.
What was it? What went on during the painting that she has this mysterious smile about?
You can imagine how much more powerful it would be to meet Mona Lisa personally.
What he says here is if you don't have this connection with every living being,
if you haven't made this commitment,
if you haven't had the experience of bodhichitta directly,
then when you meet the deities, it'd be like a thangka, like a painting or a statue.
And people will say, "did you see Tara?"
And you say, "yeah, I've seen Tara".
"What did she look like?"
"Oh, she was made of silver and she was about this tall".
"Hey, no, no, no.
Did you meet Tara, not a Tara statue?"
What he's saying is your practice of the secret teachings will be limited to meeting the statutes
and not Tara herself.
@ LTAD MO BLTA
means you're going to become a spectator
in the divine game and not experiencing it directly.
@RDZOGS RIM BSGOM STE
Then your practice of second stage tantra
which is called dzogrim--
when the divine beings, when angels start teaching you personally, they will also work on your plumbing.
On your prana, on your channels, on your @??
They will start working directly on your channels to open up your channels. That's one of the methods they use.
So you're going to meet them
and they will give you instructions,
and the instructions written here, for working on the inner plumbing, the inner channels,
I found them in John Brady's database--
and thank you for supporting that!
It's in a book called
@PHYAG RGYA CHEN PO
which is called Mahamudra.
Which is sort of amazing.
The separate title is called
@KAP PYE CHIMA
The section is Mahamudra. Which is The Great Seal.
Which refers to practice with your inner channels.
This one's called @KAP PYE CHIMA.
Another great example.
The text says,
@RNGUB DANG DGANG DANG GZHIL BA DANG
He's quoting some elementary principals of pranayama.
How to open your inner channels
through breath practice.
What it says here--
@RNGUB means inhale.
@ DGANG means hold the breath, hold the prana.
And then @ GZHIL BA means expel it.
And those are three steps
of four steps of a certain pranayama practice.
He only names three of the steps
of a certain pranayama practice.
I'd like to say something about this practice.
Lots of people in yoga studios read a book about pranayama and they try to do some of it.
And I've had yoga teachers who encouraged me to breathe in and then hold my breath as long as I can.
And then they would actually count
and it was weird because I tried to do it
and I thought they knew what they were talking about.
I sincerely tried to do it.
Then I realized it was all a mistake.
They read some book about pranayama.
It doesn't do anything to help you,
to try to hold your breath for as long as you can.
If you want to do that then do laps under the pool, under the swimming pool and see if anything happens to your Buddha body or something.
It doesn't.
It gave me headaches, it messed up my prana a little bit. It made me nervous.
These are mistaken practices.
The goal of this breath practice here is called
@kevala kumbhaka.
@kevala
means spontaneous.
@kumbhaka
means a closed ceramic jar.
The goal is--
when you're close to seeing emptiness directly,
your inner plumbing will fix itself
and then when you see emptiness directly,
the prana does enter the central channel,
as if you were shooting an arrow.
It enters the central channel.
In the weeks before that or the days before that,
you might be, for example, at your university,
and you're sitting in the library, and suddenly you realize you have not taken a breath for 10 or 15 minutes.
And that's @kevala kumbaka.
What it says here @RNGUB DANG GZHIL BA.
You don't have to do that.
That's what happens. You do breathe in, you do hold it indefinitely, and then you do breathe it out.
It's a very relaxed, spontaneous thing.
One of the best ways to get your prana to shoot into your central channel like an arrow and stay there
is to be nice to other people,
and to be kind to other people.
You don't have to--
it's not really the best method just to hold your breath and not think about other people, okay?
It would be better to be nice to everyone around you,
to be kind to them.
And then that pranayama will take care of itself.
You can still do the different pranayamas.
What he's saying is, the core of that practice
is love for other people and wanting
to get other people out of trouble.
All right, @GZHIL BA DANG--
By the way, if you're interested, what's the fourth of the four pranayama steps he mentioned here, because he doesn't mention the fourth one.
It's called @?
@....means to shoot the arrow upwards in the central channel.
He was being very tantric. He left out the fourth one.
He just gave us the first three steps.
And if you want to know about that,
then finish your 18 foundation courses.
Get some nice lam rim courses under your belt,
learn them, and then get a proper initiation from a teacher of the Diamond Mountain lineage.
Secret teachings.
And then you can learn all this stuff in a very happy and healthy way, and it would be good for you.
@ZHES PA LTAR RLUNG SBYOR
@RLUNG SBYOR is kind of cool.
@RLUNG SBYOR means Prāṇāyāma.
@RLUNG is prana and @SBYOR means "ayama".
ā + yāma
And this is one of those cases where two a's meet each other and they became a long a (ā).
But you don't know if
the two a's that met each other were short a's or long a's, and it's very important with Prāṇāyāma
to know that the first a was short
and the second a was a long a (ā).
So, a + yama would mean "not to control the breath".
And ā + yama would mean "perfect control of the breath",  to where you could actually hold it.
And that's called @SBYOR.
So one of the words for breathing practice in tibetan is @RLUNG SBYOR and it's here.
The translation is Prāṇāyāma.
@SOGS BYED PA'ANG SBUD PA BUS PA
LTA BU LAS MI 'ONG
So in Tibet, when you worked with steel or iron,
it was all done by hand.
The person was called a @MGAR BA
which means a blacksmith.
There's a good dirty joke about it.
Let's do it. I mean,
what if we get the virus and this joke is lost forever?
So I'll teach you a famous @?
are great ways to learn to tibetan.
@? are-- what do you call those?
Cliché? No.
Little sayings. Little folks sayings.
Tibetan has hundreds of them. And in fact, if you want to learn Tibetan well, it's nice to learn those little folks sayings, because they reflect the ancient language
because they don't change from generation to generation. Each generation passes them on to the next.
So this is a break from the lam rim.
You're gonna have it--
I'm not cutting the filming.
I want to teach you a dirty joke in Tibetan. Just for fun.
Say @?
@?
If you want to cut steel
you're going to have to get a blacksmith.
He's going to have to heat the rod
and then hit it with a special instrument.
That's the only way to cut a piece of steel.
But if you're going to the bathroom
and the poop´s coming out,
then the best way to cut that is with your anus.
With your butthole.
So to translate it correctly,
the master at cutting steel is the blacksmith.
The master at cutting poop is your asshole.
I hope Veronica doesn't watch this episode.
Anyway, why are we talking about that? The people who cut steel in Tibet, they have to have a bellows, right?
They have to have an instrument that shoots lots of oxygen onto the fire and makes it very hot.
So he makes a joke. He says if you try to do this pranayama without bodhichitta,
you do all these special breathing things,
you're just playing with some kind of bellows.
You're wasting your time.
You might as well buy a bellows
and sit there and do this with it.
It's going to have the same result.
Nothing.
By the way, there's no author listed
for that Mahamudra text in the tengyur.
@GSANG SNGAGS KYI MYUR KHYAD KYANG SEMS 'DI LHAG TU BTANG BA LAS 'BYUNG BA YIN
He makes a very radical statement.
The secret way, diamond way, tantra practice,
is supposed to get you enlightened in one lifetime
as opposed to billions of years.
And he says what makes it faster is bodhichitta.
What makes tantra faster
is the attitude that you do it with.
The thing that makes Tantra go faster,
is wanting to do it for other people.
Then he quotes some famous Lamas.
LCANG SKYA ROL RDOR GYIS,
PHUR LCOG NGAG DBANG
BYAMS PA LA CHOS GSAN TE
Changkya Rolpe Dorje, his name here is abbreviated,
is a very, very famous scholar of Buddhism.
He is famous for a four volume study
of all the schools of buddhism. And other schools.
He had a teacher named
@ PHUR LCOG NGAG DBANG BYAMS PA
who is a very, very famous logician,
and we use his books in our geshe program.
@ LA CHOS GSAN TE
They lived in the 1700's, the early part of the 1700's.
Changkya Rolpay Dorje used to
go to Purchok Ngawang Jampa for classes.
These Lamas had a connection with teaching the chinese emperor in Beijing.
There is still a temple there, where they would teach the chinese emperor.
Secretly, Pabongka Rinpoche was
a reincarnation of these Lamas.
It's very interesting. Of Changkya.
He was a reincarnation of the lama
who taught the kings of China.
But there was a lot of political problems
at that time, in his lifetime.
So they made an announcement that he was an incarnation of the Pabongka line, which he was not.
He was an incarnation of the Changkya line,
but they didn't want to m,ake it public.
So he was misnamed his whole life.
But it's interesting that he quotes himself,
is what I'm saying.
@LA CHOS GSAN TE, BLA MA BYAMS PAS DBANG CHEN GNANG BA NA'ANG
Now he says, Changkya says,
when I go to my teacher and he starts teaching tantra
and he decides to teach an initiation--
In the next Lam Rim retreat, which was supposed to be at Diamond Mountain in October,
I'd like to repeat that we're going to be doing
a Medicine Buddha initiation.
Online.
With permission of medicine Buddha.
We're going to have teachings on Medicine Buddha with a famous Chinese master,
a good friend of mine.
So you're welcome to come to that.
Now Changkya is complaining.
He says, I go to him for one of these high
Medicine Buddha initiations,
and @ DBANG BSHAD DU
when it gets time for him to explain the tantra to us, he goes off on lam rim!
You can feel Changkya is a little bit frustrated.
We're supposed to get this very mysterious tantric teaching and Purchok Rinpoche,
he just goes off on Lam Rim.
We're all waiting for the secret stuff
and he just goes off on lam rim.
@ LAM RIM SHA STAG.
@SHA STAG means he just teaches lam rim,
nothing else.
@SHA STAG GNANG BA LA,
GZHAN GYIS BLTAS NA GSANG SNGAGS
KYI GSUNG BSHAD BYED RGYU MED PA LTAR
And if another person were to walk in the room,
they would never-- it would never occur to them
that this guy is giving a tantric initiation.
If a stranger came in the room, I don't know,
to deliver the refreshments,
and he went back to the kitchen and they said,
"what's that guy teaching in there?"
He says, "he is just doing the lam rim".
There is nothing tantric about it all.
@GSANG SNGAGS KYI GSUNG BSHAD BYED RGYU MED PA LTAR SNANG MOD
but,
@MOD means but
@KHONG GI DE LAM GYI GNAD
MKHYEN PA'I GSUNG YIN
But Changkya later said, "it finally occurred to me, that when he's teaching bodhichitta from the lam rim
instead of explaining the tantric initiation to us,
that's the real initiation"
So that's cool. That's amazing.
@BSNGAGS PA MDZAD
And he praised his Lama for doing that.
I'm behind on this one, you guys hang in there with me.
@BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS MED PA'I KYEE RDO RJE'I RNAL 'BYOR PA ZHIG RGYUN ZHUGS THOB PA'I GTAM JO BO CHEN POS GSAN PAS
This is a very strange story.
This is a @?  @? means "Wow, that's f amazing"
@BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS MED PA'I KYEE RDO RJE
There was a-- @RNAL 'BYOR PA here means yogi.  But it means a tantrica, a practitioner of the secret teachings.
He was studying @HE BADZRA.
And the "He" in "He Vajra",  for $20, what's it mean?
@Vajra means diamond, right? What's the "@He" mean?
It means "Hey!", okay!
He dorje!
It means Hey!
@Kye!  @Kye means "hey!"
"He Dorje!"
Don't ask me why that's a long story, okay anyway...
There was a guy practicing @HE BADZRA tantra,
which is a very high tantra, but he didn't have
@BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS
He didn't have this motivation.
@ RGYUN ZHUGS THOB PA'I GTAM
but he achieved the direct perception of emptiness.
Which here is called
@RGYUN ZHUGS
Entering the stream. Entering the stream.
"Entering the stream", "seeing emptiness directly",
same thing.
And then somebody came up to Atisha and said, "oh my god, today this guy he saw emptiness directly".
Atisha is like "well, why, what was he working on?"
And he said 'he was working on his tantric practice,
and he saw emptiness directly",
almost, by the way, almost by accident'.
@GSAN PAS YA MTSAN DU MDZAD
Then Atisha said, 'Wow. I can't believe it!
@NGA'I BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS MED PAS LAN
Ya, he blew it! You know why?
He didn't have the bodhichitta that I have!
He blew it!
It's very funny.
I think we should have a skit.
This guy comes in to Atisha and says, "God.. this guy just saw emptiness directly today".
Atisha says, "What was he working on?"
And he says, "tantra". And he said,
"Oh man, he screwed up, didn't he?"
Why? He didn't have the bodhichitta that I have.
@HE BADZRA Same thing, right?
It's @ kye dorje. And @HE BADZRA.
Here's the Sanskrit for Kye Dorje.
Same-- the same word.
@HE BADZRA BSGOM PA
DMYAL BAR 'GRO BA YANG YOD
And then he says,
"Jeez, it's too bad he didn't have bodhichitta".
But he's lucky he didn't go to hell.
He's lucky he didn't go to hell.
Which means he was trying
to practice tantra without love for other people.
This is such a weird conversation.
"Hey, Atisha, this guy just saw emptiness directly!"
"Yeah, what was he working on?"
"Oh, he was working on tantra".
"Oh, poor guy. I'm so sorry."
He should have had bodhichitta.
But he's lucky he didn't go to hell!
It's weird.
It's a weird thing to say.
It's an amazing paragraph.
@DA DUNG DE YANG DRAG SHOS YIN GYI
So the guy came out good, it was pretty good.
He did pretty well. He didn't go to hell.
He just saw emptiness.
@BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS 'DI MED NA,
YI DAM KHRO BO MANG PO'I
SNGAGS 'DON 'DON SGRUB SGRUB MANG NA,
GDUG 'DRE DANG DMYAL BA
SOGS SU SKYE BA'ANG MANG ZHING
There are people who do a tantric
practice centered on a fierce deity like Yamantaka.
He doesn't name them, but for example Yamantaka,
or someone like that.
They do this mantra over and over.
And he said many of them, due to the power of this fierce deity's mantra, if they don't have bodhichitta,
they are born in the hell realms.
Or they are born as a--
@GDUG 'DRE means like a fierce preta, a fierce spirit.
The mantra has the wrong effect on them.
The fierce mantra has the wrong effect on them
because they don't have love.
They tried to do tantra without love.
And then it backfires and they get these weird results.
@CHU SHUR GYI GZHI BDAG KYANG SNGAR BSNYEN CHEN BTANG BA ZHIG GZHI BDAG TU SKYES TSUL
By the way, @GZHI BDAG means local boss preta deity.
Local boss preta.
According to buddhism there
are spirits who run the spirit show in different localities.
I don't know, like a city block or
two city blocks, there's a local spirit
who's kind of in charge of the spirits there.
@GZH means a locality like a few blocks in a city
and @BDAG means the boss, the boss spirit.
So @GZHI BDAG
and it's pronounced "shibdak".
We pronounce the "b".
"Shibdak".
He says, "by the way, the shibdak
around here was someone
who blew a three year retreat.
They did a three-year retreat
and they messed it up
and they were reborn as the shibdak,
the big number one preta around here.
Just for your information
if you try to do tantra without bodhichitta,
then you could have these disastrous results.
@ GONG GI RGYUN ZHUGS THOB PA'I KYE RDOR GYI RNAL 'BYOR PA DE LA BYANG CHUB KYI SEMS YOD NA TSE DER 'TSANG RGYA RGYU YIN YANG
If that tantrica who was practicing
He Vajra had had bodhichitta
and then saw emptiness directly,
@ YOD NA TSE DER 'TSANG RGYA RGYU YIN
He had a good shot.
He had a good chance of getting
enlightened in one lifetime. In that lifetime.
@KHO LA 'TSANG RGYA RGYU'I TSOD DU THEG DMAN GYI 'BRAS BU THOB PA SEMS DE MED PAS LAN
but instead he had
a hinayana result of his tantric practice.
What was the hinayana result?
Yeah, he saw emptiness, but on a lower track.
He saw emptiness directly but on a lower track.
Nobody says that here, but it's assumed.
@THEG DMAN GYI 'BRAS BU
THOB PA SEMS DE MED PAS LEN
By the way @LEN here doesn't mean tong len
@GTONG LEN
and it doesn't even mean to give an answer like
@?chi len, question and answer.
It means "it's the fault. The fault".
What went wrong was that he didn't have bodhichitta.
Then you can kind of see Pabongka Rinpoche
leaning back and he says, you know,
this is why the dharma is so incredibly profound.
He's just kind of leans back--
like we're gonna lean back,
this is the last sentence of this episode.
And he is just kind of cogitating and he says,
@CHOS ZAB CES PA DE 'DRA LA ZER
When they say the dharma
is unbelievably deep,
that's the kind of thing they're talking about.
Somebody could practice tantra,
see emptiness,
directly,
and blow it.
They can blow it by seeing emptiness directly.
Man, dharma is-- god, who could figure it out.
And then that's the end of the episode.
See you on the next episode!